{"test_questions": [[{"question": "Statements:\nStandard of living among the middle class society is constantly going up since part of few years.\nIndian Economy is observing remarkable growth.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes.", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Since the standard of living among the middle class society is constantly going up so Indian Economy is observing remarkable growth."}, {"question": "Statements:\nThe meteorological Department has issued a statement mentioning deficient rainfall during monsoon in many parts of the country.\nThe Government has lowered the revised estimated GDP growth from the level of earlier estimates.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes.", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes."}, {"question": "Statements:\nThe staff of Airport Authorities called off the strike they were observing in protest against privatization.\nThe staff of Airport Authorities went on strike anticipating a threat to their jobs.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes.", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes."}, {"question": "Statements:\nA huge truck overturned on the middle of the road last night.\nThe police had cordoned of entire area in the locality this morning for half of the day.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes.", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Since a huge truck overturned on the middle of the road last night, so, the police had cordoned off the entire area in the locality last morning for half of the day."}, {"question": "Statements:\nImportance of Yoga and exercise is being realized by all sections of the society.\nThere is an increasing awareness about health in the society particularly among middle ages group of people.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes.", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "As the awareness about health in the society is increasing particularly among middle-aged group of people, the importance of Yoga and exercise is being realized by all sections of the society."}, {"question": "Statements:\nThe prices of food grains and other essential commodities in the open market have risen sharply during the past three months.\nThe political party in opposition has given a call for general strike to protest against the government's economic policy.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes.", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Since the prices of food grains and other essential commodities in the open market have been raised sharply during the past three months, so the political party in opposition has given a call for general strike to protest against the government's economic policy."}, {"question": "Statements:\nThe Government has decided to hold a single entrance test for admission to all the medical colleges in India.\nThe State Government has debarred students from other States to apply for the seats in the medical colleges in the State.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes.", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "Both the statements are effects of some common cause."}, {"question": "Statements:\nLarge number of Primary Schools in the rural areas is run by only one teacher.\nThere has been a huge dropout from the primary schools in rural areas.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes.", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Since large numbers of primary schools in the rural areas are run by only one teacher so there has been a huge dropout from the Primary Schools in rural areas."}, {"question": "Statements:\nThe employees of the biggest bank in the country have given an indefinite strike call starting from the third of the next month.\nThe employees of the Central Government have withdrawn their week long demonstrations.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes.", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Both the statements are effects of the different causes."}, {"question": "Statements:\nPolice resorted to lathi-charge to disperse the unlawful gathering of large number of people.\nThe citizens' forum called a general strike in protest against the police atrocities.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes.", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "As, police resorted to lathi-charge to disperse the unlawful gathering of large number of people, the citizens forum called a general strike against the police atrocities."}, {"question": "Statements:\nThe farmers have decided against selling their Kharif crops to the Government agencies.\nThe Government has reduced the procurement price of Kharif crops starting from the last month to the next six months.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes.", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Since the government has reduced the procurement price of Kharif crops starting from the last months to the next six months, therefore, the farmers have decided against selling their Kharif crops to the Government agencies."}, {"question": "Statements:\nMany people visited the religious place during the week-end.\nFew people visited the religious place during the week days.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes.", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "Both the statements I and II are the effects of some common cause."}, {"question": "Statements:\nAll the schools in the area had to be kept closed for most part of the week.\nMany parents have withdrawn their children from the local schools.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes.", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "Both the statements are effects of some common cause."}, {"question": "Statements:\nThe literacy rate in the district has been increasing for the last four years.\nThe district administration has conducted extensive training programme for the workers involved in the literacy drive.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes.", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "As the district administration has conducted extensive training programme for the workers involved in the literacy drive, therefore, the literacy in the district has been increasing for the last four years."}, {"question": "Statements:\nThe car manufacturing companies have recently increased the prices of mid-sized cars.\nThe Government recently increased the duty on mid-sized cars.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes.", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Since the government has recently increased the duty on mid-sized cars, therefore, the car manufacturing companies have recently increased the prices of mid-sized cars."}, {"question": "Statements:\nThe university officers have decided to conduct last examination every year in March/April in order to announce the result at proper time.\nIn past the result was declared late by the University due to the lack of number of examiners.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes.", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Since in the past the result was declared late by university, it has decided to conduct the examination in March/April in order to announce the result at proper time."}, {"question": "Statements:\nThe State Government has announced special tax package for the new industries to be set-up in the State.\nLast year the State Government had hiked the taxes for all industrial activities in the State.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes.", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Because due to hike of taxes last year the State Government has announced special tax package the new industries to be set up in the State."}, {"question": "Statements:\nThe government has allowed private airline companies in India to operate to overseas destinations.\nThe national air carrier has increased its flights to overseas destinations.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes.", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Since the Government has allowed private airline companies in India to operate to overseas, so the national air carrier has increased its flights to overseas destinations."}, {"question": "Statements:\nThe Government has imported large quantities of sugar as per trade agreement with other countries.\nThe prices of sugar in the domestic market have fallen sharply in the recent months.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes.", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Since the Government has imported large quantities of sugar as per trade agreement with other countries, therefore, the prices of the sugar in the domestic market have fallen sharply in the recent months."}, {"question": "Statements:\n\nMany people in the area are reported to be suffering from Malaria.\nPrivate Medical Practitioners in the area have decided to close their clinics for few days.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes.", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes. Because spreading malaria or to be suffering from malaria may be due to mosquitoes or dirtiness. But the decision of private medical practitioners to close the clinics may be due to other causes."}, {"question": "Statements:\nRural and semi-urban areas in the country have been suffering due to load-shedding for quite some time.\nIf the Government is not able to overcome the power crisis, load-shedding will be extended even to the urban areas.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes.", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "If certain preventive measures are practiced at the rural and semi urban areas the problem will be solved. But if the same is not practiced even at the cities the problem may roll into the city also, so the two effects are of some common cause."}, {"question": "Statements:\nThe Government has increased rates of petrol and diesel by 10% from the immediate effect.\nOil producing countries have decided to increase 10% of production on crude oil from the last quarter.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes.", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Both statements I and II are the effects of independent causes."}, {"question": "Statements:\nThe vegetable prices in the local market have increases manifold during the past few days.\nIncessant rains have created flood like situation in most rural parts of the State.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes.", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The transportation gets effect due to the flood created by incessant rains in the most rural parts of State.\nTherefore, on account of this, it is possible to increase the vegetable prices in the local market."}, {"question": "Statements:\nPolice had resorted to lathi-charge to disperse the unruly mob from the civic headquarters.\nThe civic administration has recently hiked the property tax of the residential buildings by about 30 percent.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes.", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Both the statements I and II are the effects of independent causes."}, {"question": "Statements:\nThe government has decided to give tax benefits for small savings for investments and benefit accruals. However, all withdrawals of such savings are to be taxed.\nPeople have been investing more in small savings than in equity market to avail maximum tax benefits.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes.", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes."}, {"question": "Statements:\nThere was a huge rush of people to the temple last Sunday the 15th of the month.\nThe temple authority had decided to close down the temple for repairs from 17th of the month.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes.", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Since the temple authority had decided to close down the temple for repairs from 17th of the month, hence, there was a huge rush of people to the temple last Sunday the 15th of the month."}, {"question": "Statements:\nLarge number of people living in the low lying areas has been evacuated during the last few days to safer places.\nThe Government has rushed in relief supplies to the people living in the affected areas.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes.", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "Both the statements are effects of some common cause."}, {"question": "Statements:\nThe Reserve Bank of India has recently put restrictions on few small banks in the country.\nThe small banks in the private and co-operative sector in India are not in a  position to withstand the competitions of the bigger banks in the public sector.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes.", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "As, the small banks in the private and co-operation sector in India are not in a position to withstand the competitions of the bigger banks in the public sector, therefore, the Reserve Bank of India has recently  put restrictions on few small banks in the country."}, {"question": "Statements:\nThe prices of petrol and diesel in the domestic market have remained unchanged for the past few months.\nThe crude oil prices in the International market have gone up substantially in the last few months.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes.", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Both are independent causes."}, {"question": "Statements:\nThe performance of Indian sports persons in the recently held Olympics could not reach the level of expectation the country had on them.\nThe performance of Indian sports person in the last Asian games was far better than any previous games.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes.", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "Both the statements are effects of some common cause."}, {"question": "Statements:\nLarge numbers of people have fallen sick after consuming sweets from a particular shop in the locality.\nMajor part of the locality is flooded and has become inaccessible to outsides.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes.", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Both statements I and II are the effects of independent causes."}, {"question": "Statements:\nThe life today is too fast, demanding all full of variety in all aspects which at times leads to stressful situation.\nNumber of suicide cases among teenagers is on increase.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes.", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.", "ans": "E", "explanation": ""}, {"question": "Statements:\nThe university authority has instructed all the colleges under its jurisdiction to ban use of cell phones inside the college premises.\nMajority of the teachers of the college signed a joint petition to the university complaining the disturbances  caused by cell phone ring tones inside the classrooms.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes.", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Since the teachers of the colleges complained to the university about the disturbances caused by cell phone ring-tones inside the class-rooms, the university authority has instructed all the colleges under its jurisdiction to ban use of cell phones inside the college premises."}, {"question": "Statements:\nMajority of people residing in the locality have decided to protest against the municipality authority's decision to allow construction of a shopping mall in the locality.\nMany shopping malls have been opened all over the city in the recent time.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes.", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Since in the recent time, many shopping malls have been opened all over the city, therefore, majority of the people residing in the locality have decided to protest against the municipality authority's decision to allow construction of a shopping mall in the locality."}, {"question": "Statements:\nThe Government has reduced the prices of petroleum products by five percent a week after increasing the prices by ten percent. \nThe rate of inflation dropped marginally during the last week.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes.", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes."}, {"question": "Statements:\nPolice authority has recently increased vigil during the evening hours in the locality.\nThere has been considerable reduction in the incidents of petty crimes in the locality.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes.", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Since police authority has recently increased vigil during the evening hours in the locality therefore, the petty crimes have reduced considerably."}, {"question": "Statements:\nThe committee appointed by the Government on the fee structure of the professional courses has drastically reduced the fees of various courses in comparison to those charged in the last year.\nThe parents of aspiring students seeking admission to professional courses had launched a severe agitation protesting against the high fees charged by the professional institutes and the admission process was delayed considerably.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes.", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Since the parents of aspiring students seeking admission to professional courses had launched a severe agitation protesting against the high fess changed by the professional institutes.\nSo, the committee was appointed by the Government on the fee structure of professional courses has drastically reduced the fess of previous course."}]]}